[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
e-r. se radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is Zack Hatfield dods an
Australian researcher software engineer
and open- Source maintainer Zach leads
the Assurance team at anthropic an AI
safety and research company building
reliable interpretable and steerable AI
systems with the goal of making testing
easier for software developers Zach
maintains open-source projects like
hypothesis Pest and hypo fuzz in
addition to being a speaker at
conferences like Pon Zach was recognized
as a fellow of the Python software
Foundation well welcome to software
engineering radio Zach it's great to be
with you Greg thanks for joining us
today we're going to be talking about
property based testing and how
developers can create property based
tests in pest we'll be learning how to
do that in an open-source tool called
hypothesis Zack before we dive into the
technical details can you give us a
brief introduction to property based
testing and how it works with the
hypothesis tool absolutely so when I
think about writing software tests in a
kind of unit test style maybe they're
testing small units maybe they're
testing whole programs there are
basically two problems that you have to
solve in order to have a software test
the first is that you need to work out
what kind of input data you run and the
second is that you need to check in some
way that your code didn't do the wrong
thing in Python that usually means you
run a test function and the test is
considered to fail if it raises an
exception or in unit test if it calls a
particular assert method with a false
value and the second part is coming up
with the test inputs that actually
elicit that behavior that might be buggy
and so property based testing gives us a
different attitude to what we check and
a much richer set of tooling to help
computers generate those inputs for us
so one of the things that I'm learning
is that as a tester you have to think
about both the inputs and the checks and
it sounds like hypothesis helps us to do
that in an automated fashion can you
share a success story associated with
the use of property based testing and
the hypothesis tool one of my favorite
case studies is from a friend of mine
who some years back was teaching a
machine learning course this was long
enough ago that py torch was not yet
installable on Windows and so to help
his students get started he wanted to
have an auto diff library that could be
used for simple machine learning
problems but was much easier to install
and he credits hypothesis with making
that possible he says that writing an
advanced and correct library that
covered all of the edge cases would have
been impossible for one person to do
before the course started if he hadn't
had these powerful techniques for
testing it so it sounds like property
based testing and hypothesis helps us to
do things like narrow in on the edge
cases in our program under test I'd love
to learn more about property based
testing later in the show but in order
to ensure that we set a firm foundation
can you give us a brief definition of a
few software testing Concepts so to get
started for example what is a test case
and a test Suite great questions so
there are a couple of pieces here when
we say test site what we usually mean is
all of the tests that we have so if you
have your CI system set up to run a
bunch of tests on each pool request for
example all of the stuff that gets run
collectively is your test Suite A test
function is then sort of one particular
function or method that's part of your
test suite and a test case is sort of
one particular input so you might have a
parameterized test sometimes people call
them table driven tests where you write
down many inputs and outputs we would
say that that is a single test function
a part of your test suite and that the
table contains many test cases the thing
you're testing is usually called the
system under test sometimes function
under test in Hardware people would say
device under test that makes a lot of
sense can you tell us what's the meaning
of the term example-based test case so
an example based test is pretty much
defined by contrast to property based
tests a standard example based test is
where you write down a particular input
to your code then usually you call your
code on that input and most often you
then assert that the output you actually
got is what you expected and so because
you're thinking up this single example
for yourself we often call that an
example based test okay so would you
agree that many times when people use
Python testing tools like unit test or
Pi test that example-based testing is
sort of the standard approach to writing
test cases yeah I do think it's the most
common approach to testing in this style
okay so if listeners want to learn more
about this common approach to testing
they're encouraged to check out episode
516 it was called Brian Ain on testing
in Python with py test and you'll learn
a lot more details but what I'd like to
do now is to dive into our discussion of
property based testing with
hypothesis so you mentioned a moment ago
and we discussed example based testing
Can you comment clearly on the downsides
associated with this approach absolutely
so the first thing I do want to say
before I get into the downsides is that
I think almost every good test Suite
will involve some or maybe many example
based tests there really is a lot of
value in pinning down the exact behavior
in particular edge cases or even
randomly selected examples the problem
with basing your entire test Suite on
example-based tests is just that it
takes a long time and it gets really
tedious to write them when I hear people
talking about testing people often and I
think correctly say things like this
just feels really tedious I feel like
I'm writing the same code over and over
I'm just not really sure that this test
that I'm writing actually Del as much
value to the organization or the project
that I'm working on and so I think most
of the downsides are a combination of
requiring a lot of manual effort to
define a rigorous test Suite like this
and also that it's really easy to miss
the edge cases that you didn't think of
and the edge cases that we didn't think
of when we're implementing the code are
likely to be exactly the edge cases that
we don't think of when we're testing the
code I really resonate with what you
said Zack I too have found testing in
the example based fashion a little
manual and tedious and I can definitely
tell you that I've overlooked edge cases
many times so to make our discussion of
property based testing more concrete
let's take an example of a program and
then explore some of its properties one
thing that comes to my mind is that it's
frequently the case that programs have
to load in some data and or save some
data can you comment on how
property-based testing might be applied
in this General circumstance
this is actually one of the best places
to start with property based testing
precisely because it's a task that
almost all programs have to do you as
the saying goes if your function is a
pure program you don't have to run it to
get the lack of output the other reason
that this is particularly useful to test
is because saving and loading data tend
to cross many different layers of
abstraction when you call a save
function in a highle language you'll be
dealing with many layers of a software
stack all the way down through native
code device drivers the operating system
and even the hardware and so it's both a
simple invariant to express to say if I
save data and then I load what I saved I
should have the same data but it's
surprisingly complex to implement and
that combination plus the presence in
almost every program makes it a great
place to start property based testing
okay so to be clear can you say again
what is the property for this function
or program under test that we're talking
about now the property here is what we
would often call an invariant something
that should always be true no matter
what test case or input example we
decide to try the test on and that
invariant is for any input test case if
we save that and then we load the thing
that we saved we should get back an
equal object or an equal value to the
thing that we saved okay so what's the
benefit of thinking about testing this
program and using property baked testing
with that invariant or property in mind
so I think of this as having a couple of
advantages the first is that if you want
to write tests that cover a variety of
different inputs it's easier if you
separate out the definition of those
test cases from the code that actually
exercises them this is kind of a
standard separation of concerns argument
I think that gets you as far as what we
call table based testing or the P test
parameterized decorator but but property
based testing goes a little further
because we don't have to think of all
the test cases ourselves and we have
computer assistance to generate those
the same test can find edge cases that
we hadn't considered for example maybe
we forgot to think about what would
happen if we tried to save an empty
record or an empty string or List our
property based testing library is very
likely to try that as a special case due
to all the heuristics that maintainers
like myself build in and that will
discover the edge cases that you or I
hadn't realized we should check
for if I'm understanding you correctly I
think what you're telling me is that
hypothesis which implements property
based testing will actually be creating
these inputs for me is that the correct
way to think about it that's right so
what you do with hypothesis is you write
a test function which should work for
any valid input and then you describe to
hypothesis what kind of inputs are valid
so you might say any list of numbers is
valid or or any instance of this type is
valid or any object which matches this
database schema or this open API website
schema is valid and then hypothesis can
try to generate many valid inputs
according to that specification you gave
it looking for one which makes your test
fail that sounds really useful and in a
moment I want to dive into the specific
ways in which hypothesis automatically
does that before we do so can you
comment brief what are the practical
challenges or fundamental limitations
that we as developers May face when
we're using hypothesis to perform
property based testing great question so
I think these challenges are not
specific to hypothesis as an
implementation but to the ideas of
property based testing in general and
when I talk to students I'm teaching or
other professionals at conferences the
two most common concerns I hear from
people are first that it can take a
while to get used to the API for
describing what kinds of inputs are
valid when I was saying things like
lists of inages this is a relatively
simple case but if you have highly
structured data with complicated
internal dependencies it can take a
while to get use to the API and learn
how to generate that efficiently and the
second problem that I hear from many
people is that they don't quite know how
to think about finding the invariant or
those properties in their own code if we
have a business application for example
it's not always clear what kind of
invariants are there and my advice is
always to not worry about that too much
and start by focusing on properties like
the save load round tripping variant
that we talked about or given any valid
input my code should not crash that's
kind of the simplest possible invariant
but it's also in my code at least
embarrassingly effective it sounds like
what you're saying is we shouldn't get
caught up in picking the right invariant
and instead we should charge ahead with
an invariant that we understand and see
if hypothesis can find bugs based on
that simple invariant is that right at
least to get started I think people
often have this kind of paralysis where
jumping in is the way to go and I find
once you've written the simple tests the
tests that apply to almost any project
it usually becomes clear what other
properties you could test and you're
much more comfortable with the libraries
and the techniques at that point okay so
with that challenge let's go ahead and
dive into the specifics about how
hypothesis works now bearing in mind
that hypothesis is a Python program
maybe we should start how do you install
hypothesis and set it up in a virtual
environment so without trying to
describe how to set up your preferred
python environment hypothesis is
available from the python package index
so you can simply do a pip install
hypothesis or if you prefer the cond
package manager you can also cond
install hypothesis from the community
cond Forge Channel okay now one of the
things I'm curious about is hypothesis a
library that I use in my test Suite or
is it a command line interface tool or
is it both of those we Shi both of those
so the main use is as a library within
your code it just helps you write better
test functions which you can then
execute with P test or with the standard
libraryies unit test test Runner or heck
you can call hypothesis test functions
by hand if you would like to and then we
also provide a command line tool as part
of the library which offers things like
test generation that we'll talk about
later and also automated refactoring
tools for when we occasionally have to
deprecate Old options that sounds neat
so let's start with the basics in order
to get up and running with hypothesis I
think at the beginning we're going to
have to import the hypothesis module and
then there are things like a given and a
strategy what is a given and what is a
strategy all right please forgive me
listeners for trying to verbally sketch
the source code to you for those who are
less used to python python has this neat
syntax called decorators they allow you
to apply a function to a function and so
given is a decorator it takes what we
call strategies strategies are the way
that we describe what kind of input data
you want and the given decorator wraps
your test function with a kind of helper
that uses those strategies to generate
examples and that internally calls your
function many times searching for a
failing example can you tell us a little
bit more about certain strategies that
are a part of hypothesis for example I
know there's an integer strategy or a
text strategy what do they do so the
fundamental thing that a strategy does
is it describes to the hypothesis engine
which is a kind of internal API how to
generate examples of a particular kind
and in some cases that's a particular
data type so for example the integer
strategy by default can generate any
integer it's that simple but the integer
strategy also accepts optionable minimum
and maximum value arguments so you can
say I want any integer which is greater
than three or I want integers but only
between 0 and 100 and so it's not
necessarily type based you don't have to
say my function has to handle any
integer you can say actually I only want
to test this particular range for this
test function and so as well as
supporting generating particular kind of
atomic elements strategies include
things like lists where you pass a
strategy for how to generate each
element of the list and optionally some
bounds on the size of the list and
whether you want it to be unique and so
on we have strategies which combine
other strategies so a union or an or
operator so you can say I would like
integers or text and we have things
which kind of infer the data from a
schema so you can say for example I
would like strings that match the
following regular expression and we'll
do our best to generate those for you so
how does a developer decide which
strategy they're supposed to use this is
something that I think comes a little
with experience but it also kind of
comes with the definition of your test
function right so when we're thinking
about for example if we wanted to test
division we would think about well
what are all of the possible inputs for
which division should not crash we say
well we can divide two numbers so each
of our two numbers might be integers
they might be floating Point numbers if
you got fancy you might say we also want
to allow the fractions class from the
standard library and so we would say
Okay X is an integer or a float or a
fraction and Y is an integer or float or
a fraction and hypothesis will pretty
quickly tell you about zero division
errors okay I see what you're getting at
so I agree that it's difficult to
discuss these topics without looking at
specific source code but it sounds like
one of the things that you're explaining
is that I'll know what strategy to pick
based on what I want to test and what
are the inputs to the function under
test is that the right way to think
about it yeah I don't want to pretend
that it's always easy this is one of the
two things that I talked about people
finding hard or taking a while to learn
earlier but I do think that sort of once
you've thought about what you're testing
there's sort of two parts to this the
first is working out what kind of inputs
you want or what the domain of valid
inputs looks like and the second is
thinking about how do I express that in
hypothesis and we've worked really hard
to try to make the Second Step as easy
as possible though it's not always as
easy as we would like it to be I
remember you saying before that
hypothesis works with unit test and P
test can you talk a little bit about how
you would actually combine all of these
things into a P test test case and then
into a test Suite absolutely so
combining it into a test Suite is really
easy from hypothesis perspective we
don't know anything about running tests
what we let you do is Define more
effective test functions or methods and
so Pi test is responsible for finding
that and executing it as part of your
test Suite so the way we would Define
this is we would start by writing a
pretty standard unit test for division
for example we might do def test
division we'll say it takes arguments X
and Y and the body of that function just
does x / y we're not going to assert
anything we're just checking whether
doing this operation can ever crash and
then at the top we're going to add
before the definition at given so we
have that decorator and we'll pass it
arguments x equals integers or floats
and Y equals integers or floats those
arguments to given which are strategies
will then be used by the hypothesis
engine to pick particular values and
then those values will be used to call
the test function that we've wrapped
with many different arguments until we
find some that make it crash if I was a
developer and I was using hypothesis and
I now have written a test and it's
property based how do I actually run it
on my laptop or how do I run it in a
continuous integration environment can
you explore those details sure the
simple description is that you run it in
exact the same way that you would run
any other test function defined in the
same place so the decorator simply
returns a function that you can call
exactly like you call a normal python
function and that can be executed on
your behalf by py test for example by
running the py test command and letting
it be collected or if you've defined a
unit test method by using your usual
unit test implication so that sounds
really exciting I think what you're
telling me is that if I already know how
to run Pi test or unit test hypothesis
will directly integrate into my workflow
how cool is that what I want to do now
quickly is to talk about the things that
may happen when I'm running my test
suite and it could be in Ci or it could
be on my developer workstation but let's
suppose that a test case passes what do
I know when a test case that is property
based passes when it is run so what you
know is that the hypothesis engine has
tried to generate many examples by
default we generate 100 examples examp
that you can increase or decrease that
if you prefer and none of them made your
test fail if you want to see exactly
which examples we generated there's a
verbosity setting so you can turn that
up and watch the exact inputs you can
also declare particular inputs that you
want to test every time using an at
example decorator if I'm running my test
suite and then I notice that a test case
fails what will hypothesis tell me and
how will I then use that information to
debug my program that's a great question
so those of our listeners who have done
randomized testing before might be
feeling nervous here randomized testing
usually has two disadvantages that
hypothesis Works to mitigate the first
is that a random test input might be
very large or very complicated or hard
to understand in various ways and
hypothesis tries to deal with this by
presenting minimal failing examples once
we find an input that makes your test
fail we try variations on it to be as
small and as simple as we could find and
then we report that minimal failing
example the second problem that people
are often concerned about is flakiness
you want to be confident that if you run
your tests and they fail then you try to
fix the bug and you run your tests again
and they pass you really don't want to
wonder did I really fix the bug or did
my tools just not find the bug this time
and so to mitigate that hypothesis
actually saves all of the inputs the
underlying way that we generate them in
a little local database and so when you
rerun your tests we actually start by
trying to replay any historical failures
and it's only if all of the previous
failures now pass that we go on to
randomly generate more so is running my
test Suite on a developer workstation
different than running it in CI when it
comes to like saving those sample inputs
or does it work in the same way so if
you're running in CI people will often
use sort of fresh virtual machines which
were set up to order for that CI run in
in that case it's often worth
configuring your CI pipeline to save
that database cach it between runs and
in cases like GitHub actions hypothesis
actually ships with tools specifically
to make that easier and even to share
that with local developer workstations
by transparently pulling down any
failures found on CI to replay locally
if you're at a workplace where you have
things like servers or database on the
network we also have pretty easy tools
to wrap that into the database and store
it in network attached storage instead
so that everybody who runs the test
shares those failures between them that
sounds really interesting Zach one of
the things I learned about hypothesis is
that it supports something called input
shrinking what is this and how does it
help us as
developers great question so input
shrinking is the process by which we
find those minimal failing examples if
you've ever used stack Overflow you'll
know that people love minimal failing
examples because because they help us
narrow in on the parts of our code or
the parts of the input that actually
matter without extraneous detail or
complexity that we would otherwise have
to discard when we started debugging and
the way we do this is we start with some
particular input or test case and it's
called shrinking because the first thing
we try is to remove parts of it to find
the smallest example possible and so
hypothesis has a whole sort of set of
different modifications that we could
try making integers smaller making less
shorter trying to sort different
elements and we apply each of these in
various intelligent ways until we've
found an input such that none of our
modifications can make it smaller
anymore we call that a minimal failing
example because it's the smallest we can
find even if it might not be the
smallest input that actually exists that
causes that same failure and then we
report that to the user to start their
debugging process from a simpler case I
want to pick up on minimal failing
examples again later in our show but
before I do that I think we should dive
into some of the advanced features that
hypothesis provides for example I know
that hypothesis has a feature that is
called hypothesis WR and it is sometimes
called the ghost writing feature what is
this feature and how would I use it Zack
this is one of my favorites especially
for an interview like this because I
wrote The Ghost Rider after being
frustrated at a python conference a
couple of years ago hypothesis was just
starting to get popular and I was really
excited when I bump into people in the
hallway and they'd say oh hypothesis cuz
i' had it on my badge that seems really
cool I've heard about that and I would
get really excited and I'd say that's
awesome what do you use it for and they
tell me oh I'm not sure how to apply it
to my code so I don't use it I just
think it's really cool like ah like many
software Engineers I just believe deep
down that um some social problems have
Technical Solutions and so I was
determined to try to write some code
that would help people get started with
hypothesis and so that's where the ghost
riter comes from what it does is it's a
command line tool there's also the
python API if you want to build
something on top of it where you point
it at some piece of python that you've
written a module or a library or a
script and it will load that and inspect
all of the functions and try to write
the best property based test that it can
for each of those functions so when I
use this ghost writing feature it sounds
like it's actually writing the complete
P test test case for me is that right
that's right you can point it in a
module if you say for example hypothesis
WR numpy it will go and load a few
hundred functions from the numpy library
and inspect each of them and write the
source code for a test for every single
one of them all right let's pause for a
moment can you tell us a little bit
about how hypothesis actually does this
automatic creation of the test code and
the test inputs What's Happening Here
Zach well I did this in 2019 so if
you're thinking it must be AI this is
the old kind of AI the kind that
involves if statements and dictionaries
and type inference and look up tables
and substituting in string variables for
things in some sense it's a bit of a
hack job but what I do is for each
function you we'll be pointed at some
module and we'll load that module and
for each function we'll kind of look at
it and we'll say does the name of this
function suggest that there might be a
round trip with another fun fun in the
same module for example if your function
is named save we'll also look in that
module for a function named L if it
doesn't match any of these patterns
we're just going to try calling that and
checking whether we can get an error to
occur and then the second thing we do is
we look at all the arguments to that
function or pair of functions and if we
say have type annotations and we say you
know X colon INT in Python we'll be like
well hypothesis knows how to generate
integers we have this strategy which
will generate instances of a type
and so we'll create that strategy and
then we'll look at its representation
which kind of tells you how it was
defined and we can just substitute that
into the source code and then in some
cases we don't have type annotations but
we do have variable names so we also
have a whole bunch of custom logic based
on regular expressions and big lists and
a statistical analysis I did of a few
hundred million python source files last
year which will say well if you have a
parameter called Alpha this is a
floating Point number and it's likely to
be intended to be in a small range or if
you have a variable called name this is
almost certainly meant to be a string
and so in many cases even without type
annotations we can still guess what the
argument should be and in some cases
where we don't have any other
information we kind of follow the Zen of
python which says when in doubt refuse
the temptation to guess and so in those
cases we'll actually leave a placeholder
with an explicit to-do comment
explaining to the user what kind of
action they need to take to complete
this test source code that we've just
written for them The Ghost Writer tool
is going to be able to automatically
generate the source code and the inputs
it makes me think a little bit about
other automated test data generation
tools that I've used in the past for
example the penguin tool uses genetic
algorithms to evolve test cases and
inputs or you could use a tool like
GitHub co-pilot and it would also
automatically create test cas
how does the ghost riter in hypothesis
compare to those tools or to other tools
great question so I think it's a very
different kind of tool to penguin the
penguin tool tries to generate a minimal
test Suite which gets High coverage so
it will take the functions from your
source code and try executing them on
different values but the assertions that
penguin ends up making are just that
your source code has its current
behavior right so it's not really
testing the invariance and it doesn't
really think at all about the semantics
of your code and so it's impossible in
principle for penguin to tell you that
you have a bug because the test Suite
that it produces will actually just
assert that your source code does what
your code currently does that can be
useful if you need a regression test
Suite or if you want to check that a
reimplementation or a refactoring is
still equivalent to your previous
version but I think it's less useful for
getting people started than hypothesis
the variable names and so on are also
just completely meaningless in this
approach and relative to the Ghost Rider
sorry to GitHub co-pilot I think the
Ghost Rider is somewhat better at
understanding semantics and because it
uses hypothesis much more likely to find
those rare edge cases that humans
wouldn't think of or might not have been
in the trading data for tools like
co-pilot it sounds like each of those
tools may have a place in our tool
buildt but let's continue to focus on
how hypothesis can specifically help
help us I know another thing that
hypothesis can do is something that's
called fuzz testing now if listeners
want to learn more about fuzz testing I
would encourage them to check out
software engineering radio episode
474 with that said Zach can you give us
some insights into what is fuzz testing
and then what are the inputs outputs and
behaviors of fuzz testing mode in
hypothesis absolutely so fuzz testing is
kind of the grandfather of randomiz
testing techniques the first paper on it
was published all the way back in the
1980s where the authors tried to test
Unix utilities the kind of Core utils
built into all of our shells by piping
in random data just truly random data
and what they found is that a shocking
number of them would crash when exposed
to this random data more recently people
have found that using evolutionary
approaches helps you find really rare
inputs for example corrupted jpex for an
image paa library and fuzzing has thus
become a kind of critical security
research tool the interesting Insight
here is that that same evolutionary
approach can be used as a backend for
property based testing so hypothesis by
default will generate the inputs that we
try using a kind of random number
generator and a big stack of heuristics
and in the case where we have a unit
testing style workflow where you want
each test to run very quickly it turns
out that using fancier technique or
feedback or evolutionary search just
doesn't pay for itself quickly enough to
improve performance in Ci or in local
tests but if you want to run your test
Suite overnight or over a weekend then
we actually running for long enough that
these techniques pay off so it sounds
like what you're saying is that I would
use fuzz testing mode in a different way
or in a different time than I would use
the standard hypothesis property based
testing that we talked about before can
you explore that in a little bit more
detail that's right so I think of this
as being a different part of a testing
workflow right most people are familiar
with a workflow where you run tests
locally maybe the whole test Suite maybe
just one or two tests for a bug you're
currently investigating and you run your
tests in CI perhaps for every pool
request and often sort of on a regular
basis for nightly tests or hourly tests
to make sure that the current state of
the repository still works fuzz testing
with hypothesis or hypo fuzz which is
our custom fuzzer is kind of a
compliment for that we say we don't want
to run an hours long fuzzing campaign
every single time we change our code but
maybe for example overnight every day
we'll spend 8 or 12 hours of compute
time searching for new bugs and because
the way we find that is just we find the
same input which hypothesis could in
principle have found but was much less
likely to find if we run for a long time
we actually share that by putting in the
database so when you rerun your tests
the test just immediately finds that
failing input replays it from the
database and fails with this very very
rare counter example aha this means that
when you run hypothesis in fuzz testing
mode overnight it will ultimately give
us some feedback the next time I run
hypothesis on my laptop as a developer
that sounds like a useful feature can
you share an example of where that kind
of synergy has actually found a defect
in a real world program I found pretty
regularly as I been developing hypo fuzz
this hypothesis based fuzzer that using
it to run existing test Suites things
I'd already had running in CI and
locally for months or even years would
find inputs which I just had never found
through this blackbox style of testing
it turns out that the feedback guidance
makes it very very effective at finding
bugs where multiple conditions have to
be met for the bug to trigger because
using this coverage feedback will notice
when each of those conditions are met
independent L and then try variations on
the input that meet each of those
conditions I know that there are a
number of other fuzzing tools some of
them aren't customized for the Python
programming language but are rather for
binaries that may be implemented in say
C or other programming languages can you
compare hypothesis and its fuzzing mode
to things like the American fuzzy Lop or
AFL tool AFL is one of the best known
fuzzers around the other being the lib
fuzzer based on
llvm so these tools are usually designed
for use on Native code so written in C
or C++ or other languages that compile
with llvm and they usually assume that
the person running the fuzzer is a
security researcher rather than a
developer of the program so they
typically take a complete program and
have the equivalent of like one
integration test which will take the
kind of input that that program would
take just as a b string or as the
contents of a file and try variations on
that so there are a couple of
differences in the implementation as
well because hypo fuz has two advantages
the first is that because we're
integrated tightly with
hypothesis while it doesn't have these
advantages on code we do understand the
structure of the inputs to a much
greater degree so we can do much more
targeted mutations or modifications of
those test inputs in a way that makes us
much more efficient and the other is
that because we're designed for test SS
we can actually say instead of having
one fuzz harness for a single Target we
say say we have a thousand test
functions we don't need to run each of
them on a separate CPU core we can
actually run each of them for a few
seconds at a time and measure how much
progress we're making how quickly we're
discovering new behavior and kind of do
a dynamic optimization problem to
maximize the overall rate of bug
Discovery before we move on on to the
next topic maybe we can draw this all
together overall what are the benefits
and limitations associated with using
fuzz testing in
hypothesis I think the benefits are that
you find bugs which you would be very
unlikely to find
otherwise the costs or the limitations
are that this doesn't guarantee you'll
find bugs right you can still only find
bugs if there is an input that would
make your test fail and reveal a bug
that way and using this additional tool
just takes a bit of additional work
which isn't always worth it but I think
if you're running hypothesis as a team
and your team has access to a server you
should really try it out thanks for that
response I want to turn our attention
now to another feature that hypothesis
has it's called explain mode and I think
that there's an interaction between the
minimal failing input that you mentioned
before and explain mode so let's dive in
what is explain mode and how does it
work this one's fun so as background I
was actually doing my PhD on hypothesis
and extensions to hypothesis so the
fuzzer was one and explain mode is
another the reason I started trying to
work on explain mode was that a minimal
failing example is not always maximally
helpful for example we mentioned a zero
division error earlier if we have this
division test hypothesis will report to
us that the minimal failing example is 0
/ 0 and that raises a z division
and the problem is if you don't already
know what a zero division error is and
why it happens you're kind of looking at
this and you go like well which parts of
this input actually matter I know it's
minimal but is the problem that both
numbers are zero that the numerator is
zero that the denominator is zero or
something else and so explain mode one
of the things that we'll do is after we
shrink to a minimal failing example
we'll try variations on parts of that
example and then we'll report the parts
that we could vary without changing in
the result of the test so in this case
we'll say given this example 0 / 0 we
could try any value for the first part
of this so zero or anything else divided
by zero is a zero division error and
when you generalize this to more complex
inputs it turns out that in my
experiments maybe like 20 to 30% of the
time this takes a report from something
that I have to investigate a little to
understand what's going on to something
where I just look at it I'm like oh I
know exactly what's happening here it's
obvious now and the other part of
explain mode is we run under coverage
and so we can report to you which lines
of code were executed by every failing
example but no passing examples and so
knowing this kind of Divergence can be
pretty useful in cases where tracebacks
would usually be preferred but we don't
have them for some reason often that
happens when our test says calculate the
value we got calculate the value we
expected assert their equal the trace
back will point to that assertion but
this explained mode point to the
internals of the code where things
actually changed that's really
interesting you mentioned a moment ago
the idea of coverage what is coverage
and can you explore further how that's
useful in explain mode absolutely so
coverage is the idea that we can observe
which lines of code were executed by our
tests if you hook it into hypothesis we
can actually observe for each test case
each input that we try what lines of
code were executed by that input or buy
your code when processing that input and
so knowing that for each of the passing
and failing inputs can help us narrow
down which parts of your code seem to be
related to the reason your test failed
overall hypothesis has a lot of really
useful features and you're one of the
main maintainers and developers of
hypothesis my next question is as
follows when you're building a new
feature like explain mode or fuzz
testing mode how do you evaluate
that and find out whether it is
effective and useful to developers
that's a great question and it's
actually harder than it sounds
evaluation is famously difficult so one
thing that I usually do is just kind of
think about you know when I'm looking at
the questions people ask on stack
Overflow or the issues that people open
on our GitHub repo or when I'm talking
to people at
conferences I'm always trying to listen
for what are the confusions that people
have what are the challeng that people
when they're testing and then I try to
think is there something I could build
that would help people with this and so
I'm really passionate about clear
documentation but even more than that
helpful error messages because an error
message will help someone who didn't
even read the documentation in each of
these cases then for explain mode I
largely justify it by trying a few
experiments myself I am myself a
hypothesis user as well as the
maintainer and so I can often go all
right I hit a couple of bugs lately let
me try out this new variation and see if
that would have helped me in those cases
or do I think that this would have
addressed the complaint that someone
told me over a beer at a conference last
year you can also do more formal
experiments but usually those take too
long to be useful while you're
developing the tool in the first place
you hinted at something that I find
really interesting can you share another
story about how you actually use
property based testing to develop
hypothesis pretty much the same way I'd
use it to develop any other tool when I
can think of some property or some
invariant I'll often write a property
based test that says here are the range
of valid inputs hey hypothesis can you
find an input that makes this code fail
for example is there any kind of input
that doesn't save and load from the
database correctly is there any input
that breaks this particular internal
helper function that I have if I go
through every module that I have
installed
does the ghost rer work for all of them
or does it crash sometimes those are
good interesting examples and I think
this leads us to the next phase of our
show I know hypothesis is a tool that's
been around for a number of years and
that there are numerous add-on packages
and then additionally tools that
leverage the hypothesis tool so I'd like
to talk about a few of those now one of
them that I found really interesting is
called hypothesis Json schema now in
order to start Zack can you tell us what
is a Json schema and then more
importantly how does hypothesis use Json
schema to support property based testing
great questions so Json schema is a
draft internet standard that
describes as a Json document what kinds
of Json documents are considered to
match the reason this is interesting is
that it's the basis for many standards
for web apis scaners so if you develop a
website or an API that has an open API
scha that used to be called a Swagger
schema or if you use the graphql
schemers that Facebook invented in each
of these cases being able to generate
Json objects you in Python that's
dictionaries and lists and so on that
match some schema can help us generate
input data to test web apis this sounds
like it would be really useful if I have
some type of complex object that goes
into my function under test and then I
want to describe it using a Json schema
is that the way that this tool is
normally used I do know people who are
using it that way but I think the most
common use is actually VI a tool that a
friend and I collaborated on called
schema thesis and schema thesis is a
python library but also a commandline
tool that can test any web API that has
a schema regardless of the language that
it's implemented in because those web
schemers will also say what the end
points are they'll say what kind of data
should be valid for each endpoint and
also something about what each endpoint
should return and so we can generate
test data using hypothesis and using
this Json schemer extension to actually
see if there are any inputs which make
your web service crash we can also test
security properties for example if you
make a request as Alice which requires
authentication and then you replay it
while authenticated as Bob we can test
that Bob should not actually get access
to Alice's private data wow all of that
sounds really useful so I can now see
how you using hypothesis Json schema and
the schema thesis tool would help me to
test a web API I want to turn our
attention to another kind of testing
that's supported by hypothesis there's a
tool called hypos Smith if I'm
pronouncing that correctly and I think
it's inspired by the seith library so
let's begin what is seith and then what
is the python and hypothesis version of
seith seith is a famous Library
developed for C compiler testing the
idea there is that if you can Generate
random valid programs that is the source
code for a c program or with hypothesi a
Python program you can then compile that
program with different compilers and if
your compiled program gives you
different results from different
compilers at least one of them must have
a bug so this has turned out to be
enormously effective and improved GCC
and llvm and many other C compilers and
so hyp Smith was my attempt to build a
similar tool based on hypothesis to
generate python source code it's
basically a proof of concept it's just
enough there to demonstrate that the
idea is sound but it's already been used
and variations on it have been used by
the python core developers when they're
implementing new features or performance
optimizations to make sure that they
work in all cases and don't leak state
or cause problems that sounds really
useful Zack what I think you're saying
is that hypothesis can be used by hypoth
Smith in order to generate python source
code in order to actually test the
cpython implementation can you give us a
concrete example of where there was a
new optimization in cpython and how hypo
Smith was used to test it absolutely I
can even do one better than that a few
years ago in Python 39 the cpython
developers changed the paa that they
were using so it's now what's called a
peg paa and as part of that they did a
lot of testing but they were not at that
time using hypothesis they have since
added hypothesis to their own CI system
and so when I was testing it post relase
I actually managed to find using this
tool an input that would make cpython
itself Segal on syntactically valid
source code it was a particular thing to
do with backtracking around backs
slashes wow so if I'm understanding you
correctly you were able to use
hypothesis and an inspired cith tool in
order to find a real bug in the
production version of the cpython
implementation that's right okay I
tested it during the beas and found a
bug which they treated as like a P0
release blocking bug they fixed that one
but then after release when I retested I
found another Sig fault so I think that
leads me really well to the next
question that I wanted to discuss it's
clear as you've been explaining the
details about hypothesis that some of
its features have actually come from the
software Testing Research literature and
ultimately they lead to a tool that can
find bugs and see python so Zack can you
explain to us what are some of the best
practices that you've learned about when
it comes to leveraging research and then
ultimately building a prototype that
finds High importance bugs in something
like
cpython this is a great question and
trying to answer it is kind of the focus
of much of my PhD actually I think my
experience is that that much of the
research literature is really focused on
ideas about testing so people are trying
to get proofs of concept or prototypes
or ideas that could be useful for
software testing or finding or
understanding bugs and what I found
through my own work in open source is
that often I have quite a different
emphasis where I look at an idea and I
say something like well this is neat if
you have a very specific kind of problem
for example if people are only using a
subset of the language I said but
hypothesis users use all of the Python
language so I can't do that version but
is there something inspired by this you
which would maybe give me like a weaker
tool but applicable to many more cases
or many more users and so I found
reading the research literature really
valuable but always with an eye to how
would I make this work in practice is
there a variation that would be
applicable in more cases and ultimately
what kind of user interface or user
experience would make this valuable to
people who are try to get their work
done I can tell that you really care
about creating software testing tools
that can enhance developer productivity
now that we've talked a little bit about
how to transition Research into practice
can you share some general lessons about
what we should do as developers when
we're creating software testing tools to
Aid ourselves and other
developers that's a tricky question
because so often I think the answer is
it depends right it depends on the
context it depends on the domain you're
working in for example bugs are much
much more expensive if you're building
medical devices or airplane navigation
systems than if you're building a
website for demonstration or a marketing
stunt and so I think sometimes as a
discipline we over focus on bugs and we
say things like it's really important
that software be correct or there's this
kind of moral responsibility and and I
do feel that we have a real
responsibility but that the
responsibility we have as software
Engineers is not to pursue correctness
in a narrow-minded way but to think
about the impact that our work has on
society and so I think using the best
tools we can thinking about the
workflows that make us productive
thinking about whether the kind of thing
we're building is actually something
valuable for the world is really
important and then the specific
questions about testing for me the
answers kind of fall out of that broader
perspective about my work as a software
engineer so let's pick a specific domain
I mentioned at the start of the episode
that you lead the Assurance team at
anthropic first of all can you tell us
briefly about what kinds of software
anthropic develops and then as a follow
on are you applying property based
testing to the software developed at
anthropic great questions so anthropic
is an AI research and development
company where structures a public
benefit Corporation and our goal is to
develop reliable steerable and
trustworthy AI systems among other
things we develop Advanced language
models you can go to our website
anthropic
docomo which was released the day we
recorded this episode when we're writing
the particular code we do actually use
property based testing often wherever we
have things with kind of mathematical
invariance property based testing is a
fantastic way to get rigorous tests for
those I've also found that the ways of
thinking about software testing that
I've discussed can be really valuable
and think about how do we explore the
behavior of advanced AI systems and make
sure that they behave well in all or
almost all cases that makes a lot of
sense thanks for sharing that example as
we draw our episode to a conclusion I
know we've now talked about example
based test and property based tests
we've also talked about fuzz testing and
other approaches to testing and I
remember you saying at the very start of
our episode that all of these may be
useful to us as software developers so
as we start to draw our episode to a
conclusion can you offer some practical
advice about when a developer should use
these various types of testing
approaches great question so the way I
think about it almost every test Suite
should have at least some property based
tests in it so if you currently have
zero property based tests the usual
place to start is thinking about those
save and load round trips where are
places where you convert data between
different formats and can you test that
another great way to get started is to
look for places where you have table
based test for example P test
parameterize and think about whether you
can convert that to a property based
test and get hypothesis to generate some
of those inputs for you on the other
hand I'm certainly not an absolutist I
don't believe that all of your tests
should be property based and depending
on the project I've seen anywhere
between literally a single property
based test in the whole test suite and
about 80% of the test functions being
property based tests can be appropriate
depending on the project thanks for
sharing that example Zach we've now
talked a lot about property based
testing and example based testing and we
now know how to use hypothesis and tools
like py test if you have a call to
action for our listeners if they want to
get started and explore this area in
Greater detail absolutely two separate
calls to action if you're using python
pep install hypoth is run the ghoster
and see if you can improve on its output
I would bet you'll look at that and go
no that test is kind of stupid you
should be checking this or the inputs
should actually look more like that if
you're not using hypothesis look up the
property based testing library for your
language some particular popular ones
are prop test for rust or jqu for Java
or quick check for haskill is one of the
most famous and dig in the general
principles apply in any language thanks
for sharing the details about those
tools will have additional information
in the show notes so if you're a hasal
programmer or a rust programmer or a
Java programmer you can translate the
concepts of property based testing into
the specific tools for your programming
language Zach as we draw our episode to
a conclusion are there any final points
that you want to share with the
listeners of software engineering radio
I think we've covered everything it's
been a pleasure talking to you Greg it's
been great to chat with you as well this
has really been an awesome conversation
if you're a listener and you want to
learn more about property based testing
or hypothesis or any of the specific
tools and technologies that we've
mentioned in this episode make sure to
check the show notes for references and
additional details for example you might
want to listen to episode 322 from 2018
because it gives another take on how to
use property based testing with that
said let me say thank you to Zach for
being on the the program it was
wonderful to chat with you today my
pleasure all right this is Gregory cap
Hammer signing off for software
engineering radio thank you Zach and
goodbye
everyone thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
SE-R to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]